Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Middle East videotapes, 1991-2008 RL.00606
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Middle East videotapes, circa 1991-2008, 80 boxes
  - Afghanistan News, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 328, Video-cassette ME318)
    MSNBC reports from Afghanistan and on the war, includes portions of the Usama Bin Laden video tape, dated week ending 2001 Dec. 13.
  - Afghanistan News, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 328, Video-cassette ME319)
    MSNBC and CNN reports from Afghanistan and on the war, including material on Ahmed Shah Massoud, dated 2001 Feb. 5.
  - Afghanistan News, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 328, Video-cassette ME320)
    CNN reports from Afghanistan and on the war, including material on Ahmed Shah Massoud, dated 2001 Dec. 8.
  - Osama Bin Laden Tape and CNN reports, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 328, Video-cassette ME321)
    CNN reports about Afghanistan and in particular a break down of the Osama Bin Laden video tape, these broadcasts are dated 2001 Dec. 13.
  - CNN, Hindi News, Al-Jazeera News Reports, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 328, Video-cassette ME322)
    Various news reports on Afghanistan from these sources, Al-jazeera news starts at 01:32:00.
  - Al-Jazeera News Reports, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 328, Video-cassette ME323)
    Al-Jazeera news reports dated 2001 Feb. 7.
  - Al-Jazeera News Reports, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 328, Video-cassette ME324)
  - Al-Jazeera News Reports, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 326, Video-cassette ME325)
    Al-Jazeera news reports dated 2002 Feb. 7.
  - Al-Jazeera and Dubai News Reports, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 326, Video-cassette ME326)
    Starts at 0:55:00 after Zee TV soap opera.
    Al-Jazeera and Dubai TV news reports dated 2001 Feb. 8.
  - Al-Jazeera TV, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 326, Video-cassette ME327)
    Al-Jazeera dated 2002 Feb. 8.
  - Al-Jazeera and TV Asia, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 326, Video-cassette ME328)
    Al-Jazeera and TV Asia reports dated 2002 Feb. 9.
  - Al-Jazeera and Dubai TV, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 328, Video-cassette ME329)
    Al-Jazeera and Dubai TV reports dated 2002 Feb. 9.
  - Al-Jazeera and Zee TV, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 328, Video-cassette ME330)
    Al-Jazeera and Indian Zee TV reports dated 2002 Feb. 9.
  - Al-Jazeera TV, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 328, Video-cassette ME331)
    Al-Jazeera reports dated 2002 Feb. 10.
  - Al-Jazeera TV, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 328, Video-cassette ME332)
    Al-Jazeera reports dated 2002 Feb. 11.
  - Al-Jazeera TV, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 322, Video-cassette ME333)
    Beginning starts with TV Asia music videos.
    Al-Jazeera reports dated 2002 Feb. 11 and 12.
  - Al-Jazeera TV, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 322, Video-cassette ME334)
    Al-Jazeera reports dated 2002 Feb. 12.
  - CBS and CNN reports on Afghanistan, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 322, Video-cassette ME335)
    CBS and CNN reports dated 2002 Feb. 13.
  - Al-Jazeera TV, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 322, Video-cassette ME336)
    Al-Jazeera reports dated 2002 Feb. 13.
  - Al-Jazeera TV, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 328, Video-cassette ME337)
    Al-Jazeera reports dated 2002 Feb. 14.
  - Al-Jazeera TV, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 328, Video-cassette ME338)
  - Al-Jazeera TV, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 328, Video-cassette ME339)
    Al-Jazeera reports dated 2002 Feb. 14-15 and 18.
  - Frontline: Hunting Bin Laden, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 328, Video-cassette ME340)
    Original Credits: Produced and Directed by Martin Smith
    Documentary on the history of Bin Laden and the other bombings that he is alleged to be involved in, hosted by Bill Moyers. Made a week after the terrorist bombings of the World Trade Center and the Pentagon.
  - Al Jazeera 2002 Mar. 5, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 352, Video-cassette ME341)
    Producer: Al Jazeera, Qatar
  - Al Jazeera (Second Tape of Day) 2002 Mar. 5, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 354, Video-cassette ME342)
    Producer: Al Jazeera, Qatar.
  - Al Jazeera 2002 Mar. 6-7, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 354, Video-cassette ME343)
  - Al Jazeera 2002 Mar. 8, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 354, Video-cassette ME344)
  - Al Jazeera 2002 Mar. 9, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 354, Video-cassette ME345)
  - Al Jazeera 2002 Mar. 13, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 354, Video-cassette ME346)
  - Crimes of Honour, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:45:00] (Box 311: 2 copies; Box 354: 1 original) (Box 311 and 354, Video-cassette ME347)
    Film by Shelly Saywell that documents that situation of women in Jordan and problem of honour killings in the culture. Every two weeks a woman is killed in Jordan alone for the crime of honour. Documents the efforts of a lawyer in Amman to help women finding shelter from their families in prison, imprisoning them for protection. Describes the situation of particular women and the stories of women that have been killed in Jordan for the cause of honour. Also, documents the work of activists in the West Bank and Jerusalem for women who need information and aid relating to problems of honour and the setting up of a hot-line for victims seeking aid. Includes interviews with Jordanian journalist Rania Hussein, who has investigated and written about the issue of honour killings for the Jordan Times.
  - Al Jazeera 03-16-02 [2002 Mar. 16], NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 354, Video-cassette ME348)
    Al Jazeera 2002 Mar. 16.
  - Al Jazeera 2002 Mar. 19, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 354, Video-cassette ME349)
  - Al Jazeera 2002 Mar. 21, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 354, Video-cassette ME351)
  - Al Jazeera 2002 Mar. 22, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 354, Video-cassette ME352)
  - Al Jazeera 2002 Mar. 23, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 354, Video-cassette ME353)
  - Al Jazeera 2002 Mar. 25, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 354, Video-cassette ME354)
  - Al Jazeera 2002 Mar. 26, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 357, Video-cassette ME355)
  - Al Jazeera and Dubai TV 2002 Mar. 27, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 352, Video-cassette ME356)
  - Al Jazeera and Dubai TV (Tape 2) 2002 Mar. 27, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (Box 354, Video-cassette ME357)
  - Du Golfe au Kurdistan: Des Hommes Abandonnes de Dieu, PAL VHS [TRT:1:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 310 and 352, Video-cassette ME358)
    Language: French/Arabic
    Producer: La Sept Arte/PDJ Productions. France/ 1997 Dec.
    Original Credits: Un film de Baudouin Koenig. Produit par Patrice Barrat. Un Co-production: La Sept Arte, Unite de Programmes, Thierry Garrel
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #269
    French documentary made in 1996 about the Euphrates River in Iraq and the politics and problems of water in Iraq and life under the embargo after five years. Film starts off with the story of Iraqi fishermen in the Persian Gulf and the problems since the end of the Gulf War, including the situation around the town of Fao which was occupied by the Iranians for two years during the first Persian Gulf War the Iran/Iraq War. Shots of a rally for the anniversary of the liberation of Fao engineered by Iraqi soldiers. Discusses the personal situation of the family of a fisherman in Barah, who discusses the uprising in the south after the end of the Gulf War. Documentary proceeds to Najaf and Kerbala, the sacred cities of the Shi'ites. The film also tells the story of the Marsh Arabs and the drying of the marshes, the redirection of water into canals. Interviews with different people discussing the good and bad of the drying of the marshes. Also includes shots of Iraq rebels in southern Iraq, film dated from 1995, film jumps to Kurdistan with images from Camp d'Atrush and the situation in Kurdistan as well as the source of the Tigris and Euphrates in the mountains of Turkish Kurdistan. Documents the Turkish governments scorched earth policies against the Kurdish populations in Southeast Turkey. Also discussed is the dam problem in the Kurdish regions and the Kurdish villages that will be flooded with the creation of new dams that prevent the water from flowing downstream. Documentary shows an interview with Turkish President Suleiman Demirel and the control of the source of the Tigris and Euphrates Rivers by Turkey and the influence of this on the water politics of the Middle East. The documentary then shifts to Syria and the polluted water which crosses from Turkey into Syria and destroys the Syrian crops. The Turks also cut off the water to Syria with all their dams. Demirel uses the excuse that terrorists who attack Turks live in Syria. Syrian officials react in other interviews to the behavior of the Turks in controlling and using water s an issue. The film describes the living conditions in Diyarbakir, the Kurdish city in Southeast Turkey. Films also shows children in Diyarbakir and being educated at a Kurdish school in Camp D'Atrush. The UN closed the Camp because the Turkish government accused the Kurds of using the camp as a training ground for Kurdistan Workers' Party (PKK) militants and for sheltering them. The film also visits Halabja and the memorial to the massacre, on a tributary of the Euphrates. Villagers showing pictures of their children and family who were killed in the gas attack.
  - Destruction de Žirnak, PAL VHS [TRT:0:42:49] (2 copies) (Box 310 and 352, Video-cassette ME359)
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #242
    Video, dated 1992 Aug. 23, shows the aftermath of the destruction of the Turkish Kurdish village of Žirnak by Turkish military forces, includes interviews with villagers about their dead relatives with much footage of destroyed and damaged buildings.
  - Kurdish Exodus Footage, PAL VHS [TRT:0:45:30] (2 copies) (Box 310 and 352, Video-cassette ME360)
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #206
    Raw footage shot in Kurdistan, unknown cities, just after the uprising, dated 1993 Mar. 21 on the camera, including shots of Ali Hassan al-Majid's palace and street shots of people and surrounding areas, and at 00:07:45 tape jumps to the date of 1991 Apr. 6 with footage of Kurdish refugees in the mountains during the Exodus from Kurdistan fleeing the Iraqi army after the suppression of the uprising. Shows the living conditions of the Kurds during this time. The footage gives a good idea of the scale of the human catastrophe involved with this mass movement of people and the conditions involved, including the crowded conditions and mountainous terrain.
    At 00:27:00 the camera crew appears to be interviewing an old man in a tent telling his story as to what happened, in Kurdish, just a short clip.
  - Saddam's Revenge, PAL VHS [TRT:0:34:00] (2 copies) (Box 310 and 354, Video-cassette ME361)
    Producer: Shown on BBC World. Producer Unknown
    Original Credits: Reporter: Julie Flint. Producer: Jeremy Bristow. Film Research: Anna Makowiecka
    Original documentary starts at 01:30:00.
    Biased documentary film about Saddam and his ruthless attempt to come back to a position of power in the world. Begins with footage of members of Saddam's newest army, created to protect him, as they devour a wolf. Interview with Najib as-Salihi, who discusses Saddam's willingness to use terror tactics and unconventional means. Discussion of his hometown of Tikrit and his childhood. "Not a question of whether it will strike again but when." Made just after the Iraqi advance into the Kurdish capital of Irbil in 1996 that destroyed the Iraqi National Congress (INC) in Iraq, it describes this advance and the Americans inability to counter the attack. Interviews with the survivors of the INC in northern Iraq abandoned by the United States, waiting for safe passage out of the region. The INC members discuss the Iraqi invasion and the detainment and execution of people opposing the regimes. Includes interviews with Ahmed Chalabi, President of the INC. Also, includes a discussion of Saddam's attempts to engage in revenge with those who oppose him in Jordan and other areas outside of the territorial boundaries of Iraq. Tells the story of exiled major in the Iraqi army, Muhammed Rijab, who is in exile in Jordan but not safe, under constant threat by the regime. Discussion of the ways the regime has circumvented the United Nations Special Commission (UNSCOM) weapons inspections including interviews with a defector who worked in the weapons industry in Iraq and details the ways the regime got around the inspections. Also, discusses the chemical weapons allegedly produced by the regime showing images of victims, and includes interviews with Terry Taylor, from the UN inspection team. Shows, Dr. Taha Rihab, touring the al-Hakim plant, she is alleged to be the top chemical weapons expert. She denies the capability of this plant to produce weapons. Kenneth Timmerman, author, "The Death Lobby" discusses the gyroscopes found in Iraq and their use for long range missiles. Also includes interview with Rolf Ekeus, Chairman of the UN Special Commission on Iraq. Chalabi states that Saddam is involved with the terror attacks in Saudi Arabia including the attacks on the Khobar Towers dormitory. Muhammed Rijab claims he was involved in a special terrorist unit created by Saddam after the Gulf War. Implies responsibility of Iraq for the World Trade Center bombing. Interview with Laurie Mylroie about Abdul Rahman Yasin and others involved. Film implies an imminent invasion of Kuwait.
  - Interview with Kendal Nezan on Halabja, SECAM VHS [TRT:0:00:05] (Box 352, Video-cassette ME362)
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #109.
    Interview with the director of the Paris Kurdish Institute, Kendal Nezan about the massacre of innocent villagers by chemical weapons in Halabja.
  - Halabja Tape, SECAM VHS [TRT:0:32:00] (Box 352, Video-cassette ME363)
    Language: French/Persian
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #192
    See also ME80 and ME45.
  - Unfinished War MSNBC, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 345, Video-cassette ME364)
    Programming on the war in Afghanistan and the war on terrorism.
  - Genocide the Ultimate Terrorism, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:40:00] (Box 345, Video-cassette ME365)
  - Great TV New Stories: Terrorism, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:40:00] (Box 345, Video-cassette ME366)
  - Futura (Al-Jazeera TV), NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 345, Video-cassette ME367)
    Reports about the Palestinians, from 2002 Apr.
  - Futura (Al-Jazeera TV), NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 357, Video-cassette ME368)
  - Al-Jazeera TV, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 345, Video-cassette ME369)
  - CNN 2002 Apr. 16-17, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 345, Video-cassette ME370)
  - Al-Jazeera 2002 Apr. 16-17, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 345, Video-cassette ME371)
  - Dubai TV 2002 Apr. 11, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 345, Video-cassette ME372)
  - Al-Jazeera TV 2002 Apr. 9, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 345, Video-cassette ME373)
  - Al-Jazeera TV 2002 Apr. 18, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 357, Video-cassette ME374)
  - Dubai, Al-Jazeera TV 2002 Mar. 28, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 357, Video-cassette ME375)
  - Al-Jazeera TV 2-4-10, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 357, Video-cassette ME376)
  - Al-Jazeera TV 2002 Apr. 15, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 354, Video-cassette ME377)
  - Al-Jazeera TV 2002 Mar. 4, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 357, Video-cassette ME378)
  - Al-Jazeera TV 2002 Mar. 28, NTSC VHS (Box 357, Video-cassette ME379)
  - Dubai TV, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 357, Video-cassette ME380)
  - Al-Jazeera, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 357, Video-cassette ME381)
  - Al-Jazeera 2002 Apr. 13, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 357, Video-cassette ME382)
  - Al-Jazeera, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 357, Video-cassette ME383)
  - Al-Jazeera 2002 Apr. 27, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 357, Video-cassette ME384)
  - CNN Fox News 2002 Apr. 26, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 357, Video-cassette ME385)
  - Afghanistan week ending 2001 Nov. 26, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 357, Video-cassette ME386)
  - Fox News, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 357, Video-cassette ME387)
  - CNN 2002 Feb. 18, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 357, Video-cassette ME388)
  - Al-Jazeera 2002 Feb. 18, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:40:00] (Box 363, Video-cassette ME389)
  - CNN Mews 2002 Feb. 20, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:40:00] (Box 363, Video-cassette ME390)
  - CNN News 2002 Mar., NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:40:00] (Box 363, Video-cassette ME391)
  - CNN News 2002 Mar. 4, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:40:00] (Box 363, Video-cassette ME392)
  - CNN News 2002 Mar. 4, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:40:00] (Box 363, Video-cassette ME393)
  - CNN News 2002 Mar. 8, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 363, Video-cassette ME394)
  - Fox News 2002 Mar. 6 Part 1, NTSC VHS (Box 363, Video-cassette ME395)
  - Fox News 2002 Mar. 6 Part 2, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00](2 copies) (Box 363, Video-cassette ME396)
  - Fox News 2002 Mar. 7, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 363, Video-cassette ME397)
  - Futura, Dubai TV, Al-Jazeera, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 363, Video-cassette ME398)
  - Al-Jazeera 2002 Apr. 17-18, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 363, Video-cassette ME399)
  - CNN 2002 Apr. 15, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 363, Video-cassette ME400)
  - Futura, Al-Jazeera 2002 Apr. 10, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 362, Video-cassette ME401)
  - Al-Jazeera 2002 Apr. 23, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 362, Video-cassette ME402)
  - Al-Jazeera 2002 Apr. 24, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 362, Video-cassette ME403)
  - End of Mar. 25 week, Amanpour CSpan Interview, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 362, Video-cassette ME404)
  - Future Terror and Counter Terrorism, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 362, Video-cassette ME405)
  - 2002 Feb 13, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 362, Video-cassette ME406)
  - Terrorism Vol. 1, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:40:00] (Box 362, Video-cassette ME407)
  - Terrorism Vol. 2, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:40:00] (Box 362, Video-cassette ME408)
  - Terrorism Vol. 3, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:40:00] (Box 362, Video-cassette ME409)
  - Nightline 2002 Mar. 18, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 362, Video-cassette ME410)
    The Lessons of Terror
  - Wars In Peace: Lebanon, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 362, Video-cassette ME411)
  - Wars In Peace: Iran, Iraq, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 362, Video-cassette ME412)
  - State Sponsored Terrorism, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 363, Video-cassette ME413)
  - Religious Terrorism Vol. 3, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 363, Video-cassette ME414)
  - Nightline 2002 Jan. 17, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 362, Video-cassette ME415)
    Hot Spot
  - Gulf War Part 1, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:40:00] (Box 362, Video-cassette ME416)
  - Al-Jazeera ending 2002 Mar. 3, NTSC VHS [TRT: 02:00:00] (Box 362, Video-cassette ME418)